Register of the Mikhail Nikolaevich Girs Papers, 1917-1926
Hoover Institution Archives
Mikhail Nikolaevich Girs Papers,
1917-1926
28015
Girs, Mikhail Nikolaevich, 1856-1932
53 manuscript boxes (22.1 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, studies, reports, telegrams, memoranda, statistics, charts, clippings, and other printed matter, relating to White Russian diplomatic, political, and military activities during the Russian Revolution, Russian émigré activities, and conditions in Russia during and after the Revolution.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1928.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (75 reels).
Access Points
Vrangel', Petr Nikolaevich, Baron, 1878-1928.; Refugees.; Russians in foreign countries.; Siberia (Russia)--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union--History--Allied intervention, 1918-1920.
Biographical Note
1856 Born, Russia
1894 Russian Minister to Brazil
1898 Russian Minister to Peking
1901 Russian Minister to Munich
1902 Russian Minister to Bucharest
1912 Russian Ambassador to Constantinople
1915-1917 Russian Ambassador to Rome
1920-1921 Chief Diplomatic Representative of the Vrangel' Government
1920-1926 Chief Diplomatic Representative of former Imperial Russian diplomatic outposts, Paris
1932 Died, Paris, France
Series Description
- RUSSIAN DIPLOMATIC REPRESENTATIVES, 1917-1926 (Boxes 1-38)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, telegrams, printed matted and other material, of former Imperial Russian diplomats in various countries to and from the Chief Diplomatic Officer of former Imperial Russian diplomatic outposts. Arranged alphabetically by country or city
- SUBJECT FILE, 1916-1926 (Boxes 39-53)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, telegrams, printed matter and other material, collected by M. Girs in his capacity as Chief Diplomatic Officer of former Imperial Russian diplomatic outposts. Arranged alphabetically by subject
Container List
- RUSSIAN DIPLOMATIC REPRESENTATIVES, 1917-1926
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, telegrams, printed matter and other material
  - General
    - 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1918 September-1919 March (Folder 2)
    - 1919
      - January-March (Folder 3)
      - March -April (Folder 4)
      - March-May (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - April-May (Folder 2)
      - May-July (Folder 3)
      - May-August (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - July-August (Folder 2)
      - August -September (Folder 3)
    - 1919 August-1920 February (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1919 September-October (Folder 2)
    - 1919 October-1920 January (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1920 (Folder 2)
      - January-July
      - February-October (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - July-November (Folder 2)
      - November-December (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - 1920-1926 (Folder 2)
    - 1943 (Folder 3)
  - Austria
    - 1920-1922 (Folder 4)
    - 1923 (Folder 5)
    - 1924-1926 (Folder 6)
  - Baden Baden, Germany, 1921 March-1922 December (Folder 7)
  - Belgium, 1919-1924 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Bulgaria
    - 1919 January-1920 December (Folder 2)
    - 1921 January-1922 December (Folder 3)
    - 1923
      - January-July (Folder 4)
      - August-December (Folder 5)
    - 1924
      - January-March (Folder 6)
      - April-September (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Czechoslovakia
    - 1919 January-December (Folder 2)
    - 1920
      - January-April (Folder 3)
      - May-December (Folder 4)
    - 1921 January-1922 June (Folder 5)
    - 1922 July-1926 December (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Danzig, Free City of, 1920 January-1926 September (Folder 2)
  - Denmark
    - 1919 June-1920 May (Folder 3)
    - 1920 June-1922 December (Folder 4)
    - 1923 January-1926 December (Folder 5)
  - Egypt, 1919 October-1925 September (Folder 6)
  - England
    - 1919 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
    - 1919-1920 (Folder 3)
    - 1920
      - February-March (Folder 4)
      - April-May (Folder 5)
      - June (Folder 6)
      - July-September (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - September-December (Folder 2)
    - 1921
      - January-July (Folder 3)
      - August-October (Folder 4)
      - November-December (Folder 5)
    - 1922
      - January-February (Folder 6)
      - March (Folder 7)
      - April-May (Folder 8)
      - May-June (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - June-July (Folder 2)
      - August (Folder 3)
      - August-September (Folder 4)
      - October-November (Folder 5)
      - December (Folder 6)
    - 1923
      - January (Folder 7)
      - February (Folder 8)
      - March (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - April-May (Folder 2)
      - May (Folder 3)
      - June-July (Folder 4)
      - August (Folder 5)
      - September (Folder 6)
      - October-November (Folder 7)
      - November-December (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - 1924
      - January (Folder 2)
      - February (Folder 3)
      - March (Folder 4)
      - April (Folder 5)
      - May-June (Folder 6)
      - July-August (Folder 7)
      - September-October (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - November (Folder 2)
      - December (Folder 3)
    - 1925
      - January-February (Folder 4)
      - March (Folder 5)
      - April (Folder 6)
      - May-June (Folder 7)
      - July (Folder 8)
      - August (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - September (Folder 2)
      - October-November (Folder 3)
      - November-December (Folder 4)
    - 1926
      - January-March (Folder 5)
      - April (Folder 6)
      - May (Folder 7)
      - June-July (Folder 8)
      - August-October (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - October-December (Folder 2)
  - Estonia
    - 1921-1922 (Folder 3)
    - 1923-1924 (Folder 4)
    - 1924-1926 (Folder 5)
  - Finland
    - 1918-1919 (Folder 6-7)
    - 1918-1919 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - 1919-1921 (Folder 2-3)
    - 1922 January-May (Folder 4)
    - 1922 June-1923 December (Folder 5)
    - 1924 January-December (Folder 6)
    - 1925 January-1926 February (Folder 7)
  - Germany
    - 1920
      - January-February (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - March-April (Folder 2)
      - May-July (Folder 3)
      - August-October (Folder 4)
    - 1920 November-1921 July (Folder 5)
    - 1921 August-November (Folder 6)
    - 1921 December-1922 May (Folder 7)
    - 1922 June-September (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - 1922 October-1923 January (Folder 2)
    - 1923
      - February-April (Folder 3)
      - May-September (Folder 4)
      - October-December (Folder 5)
    - 1924
      - January-March (Folder 6)
      - April-July (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - May-September (Folder 2)
    - 1924 October-1925 January (Folder 3)
    - 1925 February-June (Folder 4)
    - 1925 July-1926 September (Folder 5)
  - Greece
    - 1919 February-November (Folder 6)
    - 1919 December-1920 October (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - 1920 November-1921 August (Folder 2)
    - 1921 August-December (Folder 3)
    - 1922 January-October (Folder 4)
    - 1922 November-1923 November (Folder 5)
    - 1923 December-1924 May (Folder 6)
    - 1924 June-1926 September (Folder 7)
  - Holland
    - 1919 May-August (Folder 8)
    - 1919 September-1921 January (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - 1921 February-1924 June (Folder 2)
  - Hungary
    - 1920 September-1922 April (Folder 3)
    - 1922 May-1926 August (Folder 4)
  - Italy
    - 1918 September-1919 December (Folder 5)
    - 1920 January-December (Folder 6)
    - 1921 January-December (Folder 7)
    - 1922 January-July (Folder 8)
    - 1922 August-1923 August (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - 1923 September-1924 August (Folder 2)
    - 1924 September-1926 July (Folder 3)
  - Japan
    - 1919 July-1922 April (Folder 4)
    - 1922 May-December (Folder 5)
    - 1923
      - January-June (Folder 6)
      - July-November (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - 1924
      - January-May (Folder 2)
      - May-July (Folder 3)
      - July-October (Folder 4)
    - 1926 January-November (Folder 5)
  - Latvia
    - 1919 September-1920 September (Folder 6)
    - 1920 October-1922 December (Folder 7)
    - 1923 January-1924 May (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - 1924 June-1926 March (Folder 2)
  - Lithuania, 1919 January-1922 February (Folder 3)
  - Norway, 1917 September-1924 January (Folder 4)
  - Persia
    - 1919
      - February-March (Folder 5)
      - April-August (Folder 6)
      - July-December (Folder 7)
    - 1920 January-1921 July (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Poland
    - 1918 November-1919 November (Folder 2)
    - 1919-1920 (Folder 3-5)
    - 1919 December-1920 February (Folder 6)
    - 1920
      - March-April (Folder 7)
      - May-September (Box 29, Folder 1)
      - October-December (Folder 2)
    - 1920 November-1921 February (Folder 3)
    - 1921
      - March-July (Folder 4)
      - August-December (Folder 5)
    - 1922
      - January-June (Folder 6)
      - July-December (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - 1923 January-May (Folder 2)
    - 1923 July-1924 March (Folder 3)
    - 1924 April-1926 November (Folder 4)
  - Siam, 1919-1920 (Folder 5)
  - South America, 1919-1926 (Folder 6)
  - Spain, 1921-1924 (Folder 7)
  - Spitsbergen, Norway, 1919 (Folder 8)
  - Sweden
    - 1919 April-1920 September (Folder 9)
    - 1920 October-1921 March (Folder 10)
    - 1921 August-1926 June (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Switzerland
    - 1919 August-1920 August (Folder 2)
    - 1920 September-1921 December (Folder 3)
    - 1922 January-1923 July (Folder 4)
    - 1923
      - August-November (Folder 5)
      - November (Folder 6)
    - 1923 November-1926 December (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Turkey
    - 1917 November-1919 December (Folder 2)
    - 1920 January-December (Folder 3)
    - 1921 January-December (Folder 4)
    - 1922
      - January-October (Folder 5)
      - November-December (Folder 6)
    - 1923
      - January-March (Box 33, Folder 1)
      - March-December (Folder 2)
    - 1924 January-August (Folder 3)
    - 1924 September-1925 August (Folder 4)
    - 1925 September-December (Folder 5)
    - 1926 January-December (Folder 6)
    - 1926 January-December (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - United States of America
    - 1921-1922 (Folder 2)
    - 1922 (Folder 3)
    - 1923 (Folder 4-7)
    - 1923 (Box 35, Folder 1-2)
    - 1924 (Folder 3-5)
    - 1925 (Folder 6-7)
    - 1925-1926 (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - 1926 (Folder 2)
  - Vatican
    - 1919 March-1920 September (Folder 3)
    - 1920 October-1922 May (Folder 4)
    - 1922 June-1923 January (Folder 5)
    - 1923 February-October (Folder 6)
    - 1923 November-1924 April (Folder 7)
  - Yugoslavia
    - 1919
      - January-July (Box 37, Folder 1)
      - August-September (Folder 2)
      - October-November (Folder 3)
      - December (Folder 4)
    - 1920
      - January-July (Folder 5)
      - August-December (Folder 6)
    - 1921 January-July (Folder 7)
    - 1921 August-1922 August (Folder 8)
    - 1922 October-December (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - 1923
      - January-July (Folder 2)
      - August-December (Folder 3)
    - 1924
      - January-March (Folder 4)
      - April-July (Folder 5)
    - 1924 August-1925 July (Folder 6)
    - 1925 August-1926 December (Folder 7)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1916-1926
  - Aland Islands, 1921 (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - Armenia, 1919 (Folder 2)
  - Baltic States
    - 1919 February-December (Folder 3-4)
    - 1919-1920 (Folder 5)
  - Belarus', 1919-1920 (Folder 6)
  - Bessarabia, 1917-1918 (Folder 7-9)
  - Black Sea and the Straits - Territorial questions, 1919 (Folder 10)
  - Eastern Carelia, 1923 January-July (Folder 11)
  - Elizaveta Fedorovna, Grand Duchess - Transfer of her body from the Far East to Jerusalem, 1920-1921 (Folder 12)
  - Galicia, 1919 (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - Genoa Conference
    - 1921 January-1922 March (Folder 2)
    - 1922
      - April (Folder 3)
      - April-May (Folder 4-5)
  - Georgia, 1919 (Folder 6)
  - Hague Conference, 1922 (Folder 7-8)
  - Lausanne Conference, 1922-1923 (Folder 9)
  - Lucullus (yacht), 1921 October-November (Box 41, Folder 1)
  - Montenegro - Questions at the Paris Peace Conference, 1919-1920 (Folder 2)
  - Omsk Government - History - Revolution, 1917-1921
    - 1918-1919 (Folder 3-5)
    - 1919 (Folder 6-7)
  - Palestine
    - 1917 January-1919 May (Folder 8)
    - 1919 June-1920 September (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - 1920 October-1926 May (Folder 2)
  - Paris Peace Conference, 1919 - Russia's participation (Folder 3)
  - Prinkipo, 1919 (Folder 4)
  - Romania
    - 1918 October-1919 March (Folder 5)
    - 1919
      - April-October (Folder 6)
      - November-December (Folder 7)
    - 1920 January-August (Folder 8)
    - 1920 September-1924 July (Folder 9)
  - Russia (Territory under White armies, 1918-1920)
    - Dobrovol'cheskaia armiia (Volunteer Army) - Military operations in the Don Region and Southern Russia (General Denikin)
      - 1918 November-1919 March (Box 43, Folder 1)
      - 1919
        - April-May (Folder 2)
        - June-December (Folder 3)
      - 1920 January-April (Folder 4)
    - Severo-zapadnoe pravitel'stvo (Northwestern government)
      - Arkhangel'sk - Anti-bolshevik movements, 1919-1920 (Folder 5)
      - Armiia - Military operations (General Iudenich)
        - 1919
          - February-May (Folder 6)
          - June-August (Folder 7)
          - September-October (Folder 8)
        - 1919 November-1920 November (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - Russian financial interests in China and the Far East
    - 1918 December-1921 September (Folder 2)
    - 1921 October (Folder 3)
    - 1921 November-1922 March (Folder 4)
  - Russian Red Cross - Operations abroad
    - General
      - 1919
        - March-July (Folder 5)
        - August-December (Folder 6)
      - 1920
        - January-June (Folder 7)
        - July-October (Box 45, Folder 1)
      - 1921
        - January-May (Folder 2)
        - June-September (Folder 3)
        - October-November (Folder 4)
        - November-December (Folder 5)
      - 1921 December-1922 January (Folder 6)
      - 1922
        - January (Folder 7)
        - February-April (Box 46, Folder 1)
        - May-September (Folder 2)
        - October-November (Folder 3)
        - December (Folder 4)
      - 1923
        - January-February (Folder 5)
        - March (Folder 6)
        - April-July (Folder 7)
        - July-August (Box 47, Folder 1)
        - August-September (Folder 2)
        - September-October (Folder 3)
        - November (Folder 4)
        - December (Folder 5)
      - 1924 January-August (Folder 6)
      - 1924 September-1926 September (Folder 7)
    - Protocols
      - 1921 September-1922 August (Box 48, Folder 1)
      - 1922 September-November (Folder 2)
  - Russians in foreign countries
    - General (Folder 3)
    - Rossiiskii Zarubezhnyi S'ezd, 1925-1926 (Folder 4)
    - Russian military organizations, 1919 October-1922 July (Folder 5)
    - Russian Society in Copenhagen, 1919 (Folder 6)
    - Slavic associations
      - 1918-1919 (Folder 7)
      - 1919 (Folder 8)
    - Soviet Union, 1921-1922, Emigre press relating to (Folder 9)
    - Volunteer Fleet
      - 1918 March-1921 July (Folder 10)
      - 1921 August-1922 April (Box 49, Folder 1)
      - 1922 May-1923 February (Folder 2)
      - 1923 March-November (Folder 3)
    - Zemgor (Union of Russian Zemstvos and Towns)
      - General
        - 1923 January-June (Folder 4)
        - 1923 July-1924 January (Folder 5)
        - 1924 February-1926 December (Folder 6)
      - Berlin, 1923 March-April (Folder 7)
  - Serbs of Lucase, 1919 (Folder 8)
  - Soviet Union
    - Bordering countries and national minorities, 1919 (Box 50, Folder 1)
    - Famine - Herbert Hoover and U.S. aid
      - 1919-1920 (Folder 2)
      - 1921 (Folder 3)
      - 1922 (Folder 4)
    - History
      - Revolution, 1917-1921
        - General
          - 1919 February-1920 December (Folder 5)
          - 1921 January-1924 May (Folder 6)
          - 1924 June-December (Folder 7)
          - 1925 January-1926 July (Folder 8)
        - Caucasus and Transcaucasia
          - 1918 February-1919 April (Box 51, Folder 1)
          - 1919 May-1920 September (Folder 2)
        - Carpatho-Russia
          - 1918 October-1919 January (Folder 3)
          - 1919
            - February-March (Folder 4)
            - April-August (Folder 5)
          - 1919 September-1920 July (Folder 6)
          - 1920 August-1921 September (Folder 7)
        - Vladivostok, 1918-1920 (Folder 8)
        - Crimea - General Vrangel' and the White Russians
          - 1920 March-September (Box 52, Folder 1)
          - 1920 October-1922 April (Folder 2)
        - Kuban, 1921 September (Folder 3)
        - Insurrections against the bolsheviks
          - 1921 March-1922 April (Folder 4)
          - 1922 March-1923 February (Folder 5-6)
          - 1923 June-October (Folder 7)
          - 1923 November-1924 February (Folder 8)
      - Allied Intervention, 1918-1920
        - Allied efforts against the bolsheviks, 1919 (Folder 9)
        - Blockade by foreign powers, 1919 (Folder 10)
        - Foreign armies in Russia, 1919 (Box 53, Folder 1)
  - Ukraine
    - 1916-1919 (Folder 2)
    - 1919-1920 (Folder 3)
    - 1920-1922 (Folder 4)
  - Vooruzhenye Sily na Iugie Rossii (Armed Forces in Southern Russia) - Evacution of Crimea (General Vrangel')
    - 1920 November-1921 April (Folder 5)
    - 1921 May-June (Folder 6)
  - World War I reparations, 1919 (Folder 7)